בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
Today's דף, Daf, today's דף Daf is מה, Mem Hei, 45. We
pick up in the middle of מד עמוד ב Mem Dalet Amud
Bet from the top third. So we got a little catching up
to do. So let's be focused. It'll be a fun דף, Daf,
hopefully a pretty quick one. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, או לחוץ לארץ,
o l'Chu'tz La'aretz, or
so you sell the place to a non-Jew, so that'll be leaving
him to not be keeping מצוות, Mitzvot, so you have to buy
him back and then free him or give him a writ of
freedom if he manages to escape. Or if you sell him לחוץ
לארץ l'Chu'tz La'aretz to another Jew to חוץ לארץ, Chu'tz La'aretz, you
have to free him. Now who's the question here? Who's going to
free him? Since they're both Jews, maybe rather than requiring the first
master to buy him back, you can require the second master to
give him his writ of freedom. Does the second master get his
money back? The second master also was party to this inappropriate thing
about bringing him to חוץ לארץ. Chu'tz La'aretz. And again, it is
quite strange, like okay, so what's the big deal here? חוץ לארץ,
Chu'tz La'aretz, so what? He doesn't get to do the מצוות התלויות
בארץ, Mitzvot Hatluyot Ba'aretz, תרומות ומעשרות. Terumot u'Ma'asrot. Yes. So for those
of us who live in חוץ לארץ Chu'tz La'aretz and for the
Babylonian Talmud or whatever, to see this as a big tragedy to
go to חוץ לארץ Chu'tz La'aretz is an interesting, just it's an
interesting thing as a little cognitive dissonance. And as I said, well
what? I know. So okay, but that was sort of written from
the perspective of the משנה Mishnah which is written in ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. I'm just saying looking at it through the lens of
the בבלי Bavli you understand it. The other thing to of course
recognize is what I said before, which is is that the desire
of חז"ל Hazal and their תקנות Takkanot that they made to maintain
a Jewish presence in the Land of Israel and not just a
physical presence but like a real like rooted presence in terms of
land and cattle and slaves and so on. So anyway, let's take
a look. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, Rabbis taught: המוכר
עבדו לחוץ לארץ יצא לחירות וצריך גט שחרור מרבו שני. Hamocher avdo
l'chu'tz la'aretz yatza l'cherut v'tzarich get shichrur merabbo sheni. So get the
second master to write him a writ because the second master is
a Jew and will hopefully listen to us and write him a
writ. And it does not sound like he gets reimbursed. So it
sounds like actually all the fault gets placed on the second guy.
I mean, he's the guy who's living in חוץ לארץ. Chu'tz La'aretz.
Can the עבד Eved game the system? He wanted to go and
say, oh, you know, I never wanted to go and now I'm
going to be free.
One more time?
Can the עבד Eved game the system?
What do you mean?
He'll say, I never, in other words, if he wants to go
then you're not going to punish the רבו. Rabbo. The עבד Eved
agrees to this.
Oh, so that's a good point. So תוספות Tosafot asks the question,
which is, I don't understand, as soon as the עבד Eved says
that he's okay to go to חוץ לארץ, Chu'tz La'aretz, he loses
his right to go free because he's making a free choice. If
he says he refuses to go, you can't, this new master can't
force him out. So תוספות Tosafot says, so what's the scenario that
you free him? If he's not allowed to be forced out, and
if he says he wants to go, it's his choice, so what's
the scenario? So תוספות Tosafot asks that question. So תוספות Tosafot says,
because well, what we're going to do is we're going to force
the master to free him before he even leaves because we don't
want the master to persuade him. Basically, the עבד Eved is saying
I don't want to go. So we're forcing the master to free
him because we don't want the master to persuade him to go.
So it's a good question exactly what's the scenario? תוספות Tosafot asks
that. All right, anyway, let's take a look. The second master has
to free him. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר פעמים יצא ופעמים לא
יצא כיצד Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer: Pe'amim yatza u-fe'amim lo yatza.
Keitzad? Sometimes yes, sometimes no. How? פלוני עבדי מכרתיהו לפלוני
אנטוכי. Ploni avdi machartihu l'Ploni Antochi.
I sold my servant so-and-so to this אנטוכי, Antochi, this guy from
Antioch. לא יצא. Lo yatza. He doesn't go out because he might
have originated from Antioch, but maybe he's living in Israel. Well, we'll
see about that, like let's find out the specifics. So anyway, אנטוכי
שבאנטוכיא, Antochi she-b'Antochia, this Antiochian, this guy from Antioch who's living in
Antioch, so יצא, yatza, he goes free because then you sold him
לחוץ לארץ. l'Chu'tz La'aretz. והתניא מכרתיהו
לאנטוכי
יצא. V'hatanya machartihu l'Antochi yatza. But we say the opposite. If you
say סתם, Stam, I sold him to this Antiochian, he goes free,
presumably he's going to Antioch. אנטוכי השרוי בלוד, Antochi hashuruy b'Lod, if
you explicitly know that this guy's living in Israel, this Antiochian who
has an apartment in Lod, in that case, לא יצא, lo yatza,
he doesn't go. So the question is which is the default? If
you know the guy's living in חוץ לארץ, Chu'tz La'aretz, he goes
free. If you know he's living in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, it
doesn't matter where he originates from. Let's say you know he's from
חוץ לארץ, Chu'tz La'aretz, but you don't know the specifics. Do you
assume he's going to חוץ לארץ Chu'tz La'aretz or do you assume
he's staying in Israel? So the גמרא Gemara says, לא קשיא הא
דאית ליה בית בארץ ישראל הא דאית ליה אושפיזא בארץ ישראל. Lo
kashya: Ha d'is lei bayit b'Eretz Yisrael, ha d'is lei ushpiza b'Eretz
Yisrael. So the גמרא Gemara doesn't really address what happens if you
don't know the specifics. It says, if you know this Antiochian has
a house in Israel, then he doesn't go free.
If he also has a house in Antioch?
Well, presumably, even if he also has a house in Antioch, which
is a good question, but maybe now he's living in Israel, he
hasn't explicitly told you his plans are to go back, so that's
good enough to assume he's staying in Israel. If you know he's
only here renting a room and he's in a hotel, then he
goes free. And what about if you don't know any of those
details? You met the guy in the marketplace, you didn't ask any
of those details, you don't know. Anyway, I guess you would ask
the guy. Anyway, it's the second master that has to free him.
The whole thing is very curious. If it's the second master that
has to free him, just figure out is the second master living
in Israel or is he living in
חוץ לארץ? Chu'tz La'aretz? Anyway, למעשה, L'maise, he splits. Time, how would
we deal with it? Not clear. From here it sounds like he
wouldn't go free if למעשה l'maiseh he split his time. Okay. בעי
רבי ירמיה: Bei Rabbi Yirmiyah: בן בבל שנשא אשה. ben Bavel she-nasa
ishah. Now we intersect with cases of husband and wife, get us
back a little bit to גיטין. Gittin. Okay, so somebody who's living
in בבל Bavel who marries a woman, שנשא אשה she-nasa ishah in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael in Israel. Now and there, as Michael already
alluded to, right, you can't force your wife to go with you
back to חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, and the same way you can't
force your slaves to go with you to חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz,
which makes this whole thing very curious. Anyway, so he marries this
woman in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, והכניסה לו עבדים ושפחות, v'hichnisah lo
avadim ushfachot,
and she brought into the marriage, to the dowry, these slaves, female
and male slaves, and this was not נכסי מלוג nichsei milog where
she retained titles and he just got the use of them. This
was נכסי צאן ברזל nichsei tzon barzel where he actually assumed the
title and the ownership of it. The only הלכה halacha is is
that if he divorces her, he gives them back to her, but
for right now he fully owns them. Okay, so is that like
a sale? She brought this into the marriage, the ownership transferred to
him, he's planning on moving to בבל, Bavel, so that's like selling
them to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, and
now he should have to free them.
Okay, ודעתו לחזור v'da'ato lachazor
now, ודעתו לחזור v'da'ato lachazor and his plan is to go back
to בבל. Bavel. Okay, so she transferred ownership to a man who's
now going to bring them to בבל. Bavel. So מהו mahu what's
the הלכה? halacha? So should that be like selling them to חוץ
לארץ? Chutz La'aretz? So תיבעי למאן דאמר הדיני מהו ותיבעי למאן דאמר
הדיני מהו. tiba'ei l'man d'amar hadini mahu v'tiba'ei l'man d'amar hadini mahu.
Now, we can ask this question whether you say he's right or
she's right. He's right or she's right about what? So the question
happens, let's say at the time of divorce my wife wants back
her נכסי צאן ברזל. nichsei tzon barzel. She wants back her slaves,
which I actually assumed title of. What we did is we figured
out at the time of the marriage she brought them in on
her dowry, they were worth ten thousand dollars, I write, you brought
in these slaves in your dowry of the value of ten thousand
dollars, and we wrote that in the כתובה. kesubah. Okay, now I'm
divorcing her, so she is entitled, even if the slaves all died
or whatever happened to them, I took in property worth ten thousand
dollars that I assumed title over. She's entitled to ten thousand dollars
now that I'm divorcing her for okay, to take her dowry back.
Let's say however the slaves are alive and healthy and good and
she says, I don't want the ten thousand dollars, I want my
slaves back. Okay, who gets to I say, I'm sorry, they became
mine, all I owed you was money, right? Or do we say,
no, she has a right to demand them back, to demand the
property back if she wants.
Just a נכסי צאן ברזל nichsei tzon barzel question in general.
So how would that play out here? Because here the question is
when she brings them into a husband and he takes possession of
them, to what degree has she sold them, given them to the
husband? We might be able to assess that based on if when
they get if when they get divorced if he's entitled to take
them back. If he's entitled to take them back at the time
of divorce, maybe they're not considered fully to have been sold to
the husband.
Okay, and even if you say generally it's with him, you can
say this case is different because you've taken them out of ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael and it may not stay so much with her.
Right, well that's what it says. So you can ask it either
way.
תיבעי למאן דאמר הדיני מהו ותיבעי למאן דאמר הדיני מהו. הדיני מהו
והדיני מהו. תיבעי למאן דאמר הדיני מהו, tiba'ei l'man d'amar hadini mahu
v'tiba'ei l'man d'amar hadini mahu. Hadini mahu v'hadini mahu. Tiba'ei l'man d'amar
hadini mahu, even if basically she's entitled to take them back out
of the
marriage, כיון דהדיני מהו כדידה דמי keivan d'hadini mahu k'didah dami do
we say that it's not like he fully sold them and therefore
they don't go free? או דילמא o dilma or do we say
כיון דמשתעבדי ליה לפירא כדידיה דמי? keivan d'mishta'abdei leh l'peira k'dideh dami?
It doesn't matter, it's true like maybe at the time of divorce
she'll take them back, but right now for the next twenty years
he has the right to use them and get their benefit of
them and all of that, so that's enough he can schlep them
with him to Israel to חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. That's enough to
say that they should go free, that they're sold to חוץ לארץ.
Chutz La'aretz. That's one direction.
That they're his.
They're his. או דילמא o dilma or do we
say ותיבעי למאן דאמר הדיני מהו v'tiba'ei l'man d'amar hadini mahu or
we can ask the question even if he has the right to
not give back the
slaves, כיון דהדיני מהו כדידיה דמי keivan d'hadini mahu k'dideh dami do
we say that if he can keep the slaves doesn't have to
give them back even at divorce, obviously they're his and then it's
a sale and then they go free. או דילמא o dilma or
do we say כיון דלא קני לגופיה כדידה דמי keivan d'lo kanei
l'gufeh k'didah dami since he doesn't own them for their body,
they are they're like her. תיקו. teiku. Now the question is what
do you mean he doesn't own them for their body? He actually
took possession of them at the time of the marriage, he's never
going to give them back, he's only going to give back their
value, so that's a very strange sense that it's not. So רש"י
Rashi says, the first line of רש"י, Rashi, דאי מיפטר מגרש לה
הדרי לה. d'ei mipattar migaresh lah hadrei lah. They go back to
her. But they don't go back to her. We're saying הדיני מהו
hadini mahu that he can basically say I'm just giving you their
value. So I don't really understand, I have to say, this side
of the question. I don't know. Like a rental. But it's not.
He never gives back he she can insist on getting the slaves
back and she doesn't get them back. He only gives back their
value. So the fact that he would have to in the end
pay for their value means that they're not his? It's like I
bought something and I never paid for it, and I'll pay for
it, it's now a gift, and if in the end something happens
it'll have been a sale, but either way I'm taking full possession
of it.
Could she have written into the כתובה kesubah that לגופם l'gufam I'm
getting them back in case of a divorce?
Maybe. I don't know what happens if she would explicitly state... But
we're not talking about that case. I don't really understand this.
Yeah. Isn't this something to her advantage regardless of what happens to
that property? Yes.
Yes. The fact that they're their value is assessed and that's why
they're called צאן ברזל, Tzon Barzel, they are protected assets. She is
she is insured that she will get their full value back. The
question is let's say she wants them back themselves, right? And let's
say their value goes up, right?
So you could maybe say that she wants to get what she
put the security.
Yes. Yes, you could, and that's exactly the question דהני מנא דהני
מה, De-Hani Mana De-Hani Ma, that's exactly that question. Okay. אמר רב
אבא. Amar Rav Abba. שדרי רבי יוחנן. Shadrei Rabbi Yochanan. Rabbi Yochanan
taught me: עבד שיצא אחר רבו לסוריא, Eved she-yatza achar rabo l'Suriya,
the עבד Eved followed his master to סוריא, Suriya, and סוריא Suriya
is like you know this area like this Syria probably or something
there those areas around ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel where toward conquered by
דוד המלך Dovid HaMelech that had like this quasi ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisroel status, okay? ומכר שם רבו יצא לחירות, U'machar sham rabo yatza
l'cherut,
and his master sold him, he goes free because being sold to
סוריא Suriya if you remember we said this way in the first
פרק, Perek, right? המוכר עבדו לסוריא, Ha'mocher avdo l'Suriya, לסוריא Suriya you
know he's you know he's יצא לחירות. Yatza l'cherut. It's like חוץ
לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. Okay.
So therefore so the חידוש Chiddush is not just if you sell
him to סוריא Suriya he goes free, but that even though he
went willingly to סוריא, Suriya, you don't say well you already made
that choice yourself, right, you can't blame the master. No, nevertheless he
goes free. The question is when he went to סוריא Suriya was
he going to settle there or were they just going on a
trip? Right? That would depend, right? Because the question is did the
עבד Eved choose on his own to live in סוריא? Suriya? If
they were just going for a trip, then he can't blame the
עבד Eved for having been in סוריא. Suriya. So it says והתניא
רבי חייא איבד את זכותו, V'hatanya Rabbi Chiya ibbed et zechuto, when
he went to סוריא Suriya the slave lost his right. לא קשיא.
Lo kashya. כאן שדעת רבו לחזור כאן שאין דעת רבו לחזור, Kan
she-da'at rabo lachzor kan she-ein da'at rabo lachzor, like we just said.
If the master was going just on a little on a trip
and he took his slave with him, then the slave didn't lose
any right. I wasn't planning on leaving ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisroel, we
were just going on a trip and then my master sold me
to סוריא, Suriya, he sold me to חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, he
assigned my state to חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, okay, my fate, whereas
if they they were planning to moving to סוריא Suriya and the
עבד Eved willingly went, then it's the עבד's Eved own fault. He
doesn't go free now that he's sold. Okay. Right.
But how would you know if they that he went for free,
yeah, that he didn't or did want to go?
You mean what would be the default if the master didn't tell
him, if the master whatever and he just went? I mean my
master's going, I'm going with him, I'm supposed to ask my master
what his plans are? Right. So I would that's a good question.
I don't know, I would assume by default we we sort of
you know like like it's sort of like the previous customs. What
do you do בספק? Be-safek? I don't know, my my gut is
that is the default is that we would favor the slave like
unless we could prove that he had forfeited his rights, but I
don't know.
So so you would assume meaning like we assume he didn't want
to go?
We would assume that he was not planning on he didn't like
if you don't know that you're moving there and willingly moving there
you're just following your master, right? I don't but I don't know
it's a good question. Okay yes. Interestingly there's not a lot of
responsa literature on this. Yes.
In all these cases what are we assuming this is like the
rabbinic decision but in reality the owner is not going to give
this guy up or or he wouldn't have even bought him in
the first place?
Yeah I mean that's right that's like the irony about it like
the whole point before about you have to try to buy him
back at ten times the value like it's very nice to say
we force the master to sell him but like as you're saying
like if anybody knows that if I buy him I'm going to
have to free him, who's buying him? So obviously I mean maybe
so the one scenario that could work is like I bought him
in ignorance of the law and I was informed of the law
and I'm a פרום Frum guy so I'm going to do it
right? But any other scenario either I'm not buying him or I'm
but maybe that was the point. Good. If this תקנה Takana is
going to mean that you're going to not buy him then that's
exactly what we want is for you to not buy him. And
if you violate it and thought you would get away with it
and we can exert some power and control over you then we're
going to do something about it, right. Yeah. But yeah it's an
excellent point. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. והתניא
V'hatanya
okay כאן שאין דעת רבו לחזור. Kan she-ein da'at rabo lachzor. והתניא
V'hatanya we teach in a ברייתא Baraita יוצא עבד אחר רבו לסוריא,
Yotze eved achar rabo l'Suriya, an עבד Eved follows his master to
סוריא, Suriya, so the גמרא Gemara interrupts the ברייתא: Baraita: יוצא? Yotze?
He follows like he has to follow? לא סגי דלא נפיק? Lo
sagi d'lo nafik? It's not enough that he should follow, I mean
is he required? והתנן ואינו כה מוציאין. Vatnan v'eino ko motzi'in. You
cannot force anybody to go out of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisroel. Your
husband can't force his wife, he can't force his slaves. So what
does it mean you have to follow your master? Like he and
the כתובה? Ketubah? Right exactly. אלא יצא העבד. Ela yatza ha-eved. No
what it means is if the slave did follow אחר רבו לסוריא
Achar rabo l'Suriya ומכר שם רבו, U'machar sham rabo, the master sold
him, אם דעת רבו לחזור, Im da'at rabo lachzor, if the master
was planning on returning, כופין אותו, Kofin oto, then you force the
second guy to free him because then he the slave had not
willingly left had not left to resettle outside of ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisroel. ואם אין דעת רבו לחזור, V'im ein da'at rabo lachzor, but
if the master was not planning on returning so the slave willingly
chose to leave ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel and to settle outside of
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisroel, then he lost his right, אין כופין אותו,
Ein kofin oto, you do not force the second guy to free
him. אמר רב ענן. Amar Rav Anan. שמענא מיני דמר שמואל תרתי.
Shma'na minei d'Mar Shmuel tarti. I've heard from I've heard from שמואל
Shmuel תרתי Tarti two rulings: חדא הא, Chada ha, one this ruling
about about like you know that if you're forcing or whatever yes
freeing the slave, והאידך V'idach and the other... דאתמר de-itmar המוכר שדה
בשנת היובל hamocher sadeh bishnas hayovel if somebody sold the field during
יובל, Yovel, עד יובל, ad yovel, the field's returned. Let's say you
tried to sell a field during the שמיטה Shmita year. עצמה. Atzma.
רב אמר מכורה ויוצאה, Rav amar mechura ve-yatza, the sale goes through
and then a second later it reverses. Okay, it was a good
sale and then it goes back to the original owner. The נפקא
מינה nafka mina is, well, one נפקא מינה nafka mina is you
keep the money because it was a good sale. The other נפקא
מינה nafka mina is that if you you can sell מטלטלין metaltelin
through a קנין קרקע. kinyan karka. So if I sell you by
taking possession of my field here, I'm also selling you my car
and my and my goats or whatever, then they don't go back
to the guy but you get to keep the car, keep the
car and the goats, because that act of קנין kinyan on the
קרקע karka worked for other things. So Rav said it was a
legitimate act of קנין kinyan and then it just goes back. ושמואל
אמר אינה מכורה כל עיקר. u-Shmuel amar eino mechura kol ikkar. No
no no, the sale doesn't go through. Okay now, so those are
the two cases where one is you sold a slave to חוץ
לארץ Chutz La'aretz and the other is you sold a field during
יובל. Yovel. One minute, בחדא
הדרי זביני.
bechada
hadra
zvini.
In one case the sale goes through but it gets reversed. ובחדא
לא הדרי זביני. ubichada lo hadra zvini. And the other it, you
know, it doesn't get reversed, meaning meaning the, I'm sorry, הדרי זביני
hadra zvini means one minute. Sale goes through. No no no. No
no, meaning the sale goes back, no I misstated that. Meaning the
money, meaning meaning the money goes back to the purchaser. In one
case the money goes back to the purchaser and in the other
case the money does not go back. So here we're finally asking
the question, right? I went ahead and I bought this slave and
now I'm going to have to free him. Okay, do I get
my money back? That's a good question, right? So he says you
have these two cases. I bought my slave I have to free
him, do I get my money back? Okay. And the other question
is I sold this field during the יובל, Yovel, right, or I
bought this field during the יובל Yovel and it wasn't good, do
I get my money back? So those are the two cases. And
in one case Shmuel says you get your money back, and one
case he says you don't. Now it should seem pretty obvious which
is which, because in the one case Shmuel says the sale didn't
go through by the field. So if the sale didn't go through
I get my money back. In the other case Shmuel says I,
the second master, or the ברייתא Braita says have to free him.
So if I, the second master, have to free him obviously the
sale went through. So I don't get my money back and now
I have to free him. And that's what the גמרא's Gemara going
to conclude. Why there was a doubt is not so clear.
Well I'll say this. In other words, you know, the reason why
I would have to free him is because, you know, like it
seems like he was purchasing him as a slave and you know
people are going to think he's a slave, so therefore I have
to free him, you know, just so there'll be no doubt in...
Oh maybe, but then the first master would also have to free
him.
What I'm thinking is though what I find it's very curious because
you know let's say for instance I'm going to I'm going to,
you know, to buy buy real estate, right? Right. So sometimes, you
know, I kind of have to do like a blind shop because
like the people don't know the the people working there don't know
that it's being sold. So you know so you go and you
look at it and you know whatever, but you can't really talk
to the people. So I so I was thinking that sometimes that
might be the case with a slave. In other words, you know,
so I'm asking this guy, yeah yeah yeah, he wants to go.
It turns out he didn't want to go. Like why should I
be penalized because this guy's sort of lying to me, you know,
I mean I didn't even have an opportunity to ask the slave.
So I'm assuming this guy's legitimate...
No no no no no. So you're dealing with a case... so
okay what's confusing you is you're dealing with the immediately previous case
which was the question of whether the slave willingly went or not.
We're not dealing with that case. We're dealing with the simple case
that I sold a slave to חוץ. Chutz. You're living in חוץ,
Chutz, I'm living in Israel, I'm selling my slave to you. And
you know I live in Israel. And I you know I live
in Israel, everybody knows everything. And the הלכה halakha is you're going
to be forced to free him. Can you get your money back
now? Okay, so the answer should be obvious. Of course not. You
know, you know, it was it's clear the sale went through because
you're forced to free him. So that so and you did the
wrong thing, I did the wrong thing too, I sold him but
you did the wrong thing you bought him and you don't get
your money back. So let's see let's just get through this גמרא,
Gemara, okay? And then he says: אמר רב יוסף Amar Rav Yosef
ולא ידענא v'lo yadana and I don't know הי מנייהו hai mineihu
which one which one do you get your money back which one
don't you. אמר אביי Amar Abaye נחזי אנן nechezei anan let's figure
this out ourselves. דתניא בברייתא de-tanya bevraita we taught in the ברייתא:
Braita: המוכר עבדו לחוץ לארץ יצא לחירות וצריך גט שחרור מרבו שני.
hamocher avdo lachutz la'aretz yatza lacheres vetzarich get shichrur merabbo sheni. Thank
you very much. The second master is the one who frees him.
Okay. שמע מינה shma minei תני רבו שני. tanya rabbo sheni. The
second master purchased him ולא הדרי זביני v'lo hadra zvini he doesn't
get his money back, he loses he's the one that loses out
and he has to free him. דכי אמר שמואל התם אינה מכורה
ומעות חוזרין. de-chi amar Shmuel hatam eino mechura umos chozrin. Okay and
when does and in the case by שמיטה Shmita Shmuel is saying
the sale didn't go through and the money goes back, obviously if
the sale doesn't go through the money goes back. So isn't that
pretty obvious? I mean it's obvious from both cases. The שמיטה Shmita
one is the sale didn't go through and the frame in the
other is the second master has to free him. דרב ענן de-Rav
Anan ברייתא לא שמיע ליה. Braita lo shmia lei. Okay, and רב
ענן Rav Anan so how did רב ענן Rav Anan not know
this? Number one is he didn't have know the ברייתא Braita that
says the second master freed him. So maybe that's true, from the
משנה Mishna you might get the impression that the first master frees
him. Okay, you could easily read our משנה Mishna that if you
sold him to חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz the sale didn't go through
and you have to free him. So from the משנה Mishna it's
not clear. So number one that's a good that's a possible read.
And how could you say by שמיטה Shmita if I sell it
the money doesn't go back? How could that have been and Shmuel
said the sale didn't go through? ואי דשמואל v'im de-Shmuel and if
it's Shmuel's teaching about that on שמיטה Shmita the sale doesn't go
through, ממאי דאינה מכורה מעות חוזרין? mimmay de-eino mechura mos chozrin? I
know that the sale didn't go through. through, but that doesn't necessarily
mean the money goes back. How could the sale not go through
and the money not go back? דאינה מכורה מיהדר זוזי? De-einah mechura
mihadar zuzei? דילמא אינה מכורה ומתנה נינהו? Dilma einah mechura u-matanah ninhu?
Maybe I should say look you knew what you were doing, you
knew the sale wouldn't go through, you went through this little, you
know, play anyway, you went through these, you know, you went through
the motions. So why did you give him money if you knew
the sale wouldn't go through? It must be that the money was
really just a gift. Maybe that was your way. He wouldn't accept
a gift from you, so you did this little fake sale of
land, who knows why, but you gave him money at a time
when the sale wouldn't go through, let's consider that a gift and
the money won't go back. Let's just finish it. מידי דהוה אמקדש
את אחותו, Midei de-hava a-mekadesh et achoto, like what happens if you
give your sister money to marry her? דאיתמר המקדש את אחותו, De-itmar
ha-mekadesh et achoto, you give your sister a diamond ring and you
say הרי את מקודשת לי. Harei at mekudeshet li. רב אמר מעות
חוזרים, Rav amar ma'ot chozrin, you get your diamond ring back, ושמואל
אמר מעות מתנה. u-Shmuel amar ma'ot matanah. No, it's a gift. אמר
ליה אביי לרב יוסף, Amar lei Abaye le-Rav Yosef, okay, anyway, so
therefore since you know you can't marry your sister, so therefore we
interpret it as a gift. So the fact that שמואל Shmuel says
when you sell a field on שמיטה Shmita it's the sale doesn't
go through, does not prove that the money goes back. It would
have been possible to interpret that case and say the money is
a gift. But we don't. In that case the sale doesn't go
through, the money goes back. Now in our case, when you sell
your slave to חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, if you just had the
משנה, Mishnah, you could easily have read it that the sale didn't
go through and the first master has to free him. We find
out from the ברייתא, Braita, not that way, that the sale did
go through and that, you know, the sale did go through and
the second master has to free him and it's the second guy
who loses out on his money. So now that prompts the גמרא
Gemara to say why is the second guy the one who loses
out? Why should the buyer lose out? Why don't we say, no,
it didn't go through and the first guy has to free him?
Him both the same. Both him like the שמיטה Shmita case.
Yeah, but it's also but here it's even but forget
the שמיטה Shmita parallel, it's just more like a like an ethical
question. Like who is the right one to that has to be
punished here? Right? Because we're you know if if in when I
sold it to you and you're in חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, I
got my money. You lost your money. Why should right? So if
the sale goes or doesn't go through and who frees him is
a question of who is the one that is being fined, who
is the one that is being punished? So that's now the question.
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה
אביי לרב יוסף, Amar lei Abaye le-Rav Yosef, מאי חזית דקנסינן ללוקח?
mai chazit de-kansinan le-loke'ach? Why do we say the sale goes through
and the second master has to free him and he loses out
on his money? Why does the purchaser is the one who's fined?
נקנסינה למוכר. Nikhansinah le-mocher. Let's fine the seller and say that it's
the sale didn't go through and the seller has to free him.
אמר ליה לאו עכברא גנב אלא חורא גנב. Amar lei lav achbara
ganav ela chura ganav. Yes, right, right, right. It's not it's not
the weasel that steals, it's the hole that steals.
Not the hole wouldn't be a weasel.
Right, you provided him the opportunity. Can I finish reading the גמרא?
Gemara? Okay. אמר ליה, Amar lei, I appreciate that. אמר ליה אי
לאו עכברא חורא מאי עביד? Amar lei ei lav achbara chura mai
avid? If it wasn't for the weasel or whatever the hole wouldn't
do anything. The hole doesn't do anything. The weasel's the גנב, ganav,
he's the initiator, right? And it's so fine, he needs the opportunity,
but he's still the initiator. Now it's funny to say it that
way by a sale because, you know, I think somehow it's interesting
question about about the way we use verbs, right? Like somehow מוכר
המוכר המוכר mocher ha-mocher ha-mocher sounds like he's the initiator. But that
doesn't mean that's true at all. Right, what makes you think that?
I can approach you. Right, what makes you think that the person
who's initiating I could be the one looking around for good deals
with slaves, I could be the initiator, I could pressure you to
sell. Right, the very fact that it looks, I mean besides the
general question, right? If like like the גמרא Gemara has this if
like you know, I don't know, I'm actually a like a you
know a a burglar and you purchase my stolen goods. So clearly
there, I'm the one doing something wrong. You're providing me the opportunity
to make a profit. If
you didn't give me that opportunity, I wouldn't steal anything. But nevertheless,
I'm clearly the one doing something wrong and you're just the opportunity.
I'm the one doing something wrong. But here it's strange that we
look at the seller as the one doing something wrong and the
buyer as providing him the opportunity, you know, because how do you
know the buyer isn't the one that's coming and approaching this guy
and saying please sell me your slave and he's not the one
that's initiating? Both sides are supposed to know. Both sides are supposed
to know. Anyway, it's interesting that we look at the seller, I
guess he's my slave and I'm doing something to him. I'm ultimately
the one that's doing something to my slave, I'm right now the
one who owns him. Anyway, so we look if we look at
the seller as the one who's like the one transgressing and the
buyer as the one who's providing the opportunity, then it really is
a good question why prevent put more of the punishment on the
one who's providing the opportunity. And let's see what the גמרא'ס Gemara's
answer is. Everybody's doing it in bad faith. But you don't know
that. Nobody we don't know who knows who's doing something wrong. But
the guy who who owns the slave in Israel knows that he's
doing it. How does he know? Because there's a rule that he
can't. And so the buyer also knows that rule. But does he?
But does the seller? The same way the buyer could be ignorant,
the seller could be ignorant. But then you still don't know who's
ignorant here.
Okay, so that's true by both sides.
Why are you assuming the buyer
is the one who
knows the rules and not the seller?
But the question then is who is initiating? But why is the
buyer the initiator, why is the seller the initiator?
Maybe the buyer's the initiator? The analogy here is like- but you
really have to find all this out. Right! But in other words,
there shouldn't be one- when I go ahead
and I go to
Amazon and I buy all this- all this stuff that's not good
for me, okay, who's the initiator and who's providing the opportunity?
I'm the initiator, they're providing the opportunity, right? So is the buyer
the
initiator or the seller the initiator? But you can't have a rule
then.
You gotta look at each case
and say who's the initiator.
I know! But so why have we made a flat decision that
we're punishing the buyer?
Why are we making that decision? Okay? All right! This is losing
חוצה. Chutza. Okay, so the answer is- so let's see the- can
we see the answer? אמר ליה, Amar lei, okay, אי לאו עכברא
חורא מנא ליה, ei lav achbara chora mana lei, מסתברא היכא דאיכא
איסורא התם קנסינן. mistabra heicha de-ika issura hatam kansinan. So where the
איסור issur is, that's
where we fine, meaning that you're the one who's living
in חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, you're the problematic situation. We're not thrilled
with the fact that you're living in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz in
general, you're the one who's bringing him into this problematic situation.
So somehow that's the locus of the problem.
A shore sin, four or five, right? I buy your stolen... right,
but you don't want to pay four and five. Exactly, exactly. Anyway,
so somehow that is seen as the locus of the problem, because
חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz is the problem. It's a very interesting, sort
of, I think, a moral type of a whatever justice type of
a question. There were a couple of questions. One by one small
point. What would be the motive in the case of the יובל
Yovel sale of the field if it's not מטלטלין אגב קרקע? metaltelin
agav karka? Like why would I even?
No good, no good reason, unless you were ignorant. Same thing. It
would have to be either a fake way to give
a gift or you were ignorant. Why would you מקדש mekadesh your
sister? Right? I mean, they had a fun time exploring these. I
don't know if there was always good reasons why people would do
this. Right.
You know my joke about that whole thing about like why are
you doing- why are you selling it as- you know- the money
goes back. The guy comes to Saudi and says, "I'll sell you
the Brooklyn Bridge."
"Really? Brooklyn Bridge? How much?" He says, "Only a million dollars, a
real-" "Wow, a million dollars, great!" He takes out his checkbook, he
writes- he says, "You got a pen?" gives him a pen, writes
down a check for a million dollars, gives it to him. They
both walk away. So his friend says to him, says, "What the
heck were you doing? You bought a bridge that he doesn't own
with money that you don't have." He says, "What? And this pen
is nothing?" So okay, anyway, there you go, that's why you did
it. Okay, anyway, moving on. All right, so let's see the גמרא.
Gemara. ההוא עבדא דערק מחוץ לארץ לארץ. hahu avda de-ark mi-Chutz La'aretz
le-Aretz. Your bank account. Okay, so there was a- there was a
slave- now- now you're going to appreciate this because Dave, I think
you were asking me about whatever happens to the פסוק pasuk about
the slave that runs away. So we're finally going to deal with
that פסוק, pasuk, right? ההוא עבדא דערק מחוץ לארץ לארץ. hahu avda
de-ark mi-Chutz La'aretz le-Aretz. A slave ran from חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz
to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. אתא מריה בתריה, ata marei batrei, so
the master came right running after him to go take him back.
אתא לקמיה דרבי אמי. ata lekamei de-Rabbi Ami. The master, who came
from חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz.
אמר ליה, amar lei, he
said to him, נכתוב לך שטרא אדמי, nichtov lach shtra admei, listen
buddy, I'll write you a writ for his value so you can
at least not lose out. וכתוב ליה גיטא דחירותא. ve-chtov lei gita
de-cheiruta. I don't know, the community would raise the money or something.
And you write him a writ of freedom. Okay? ואילו, ve-ilu, and
if you don't agree to that, so at least you're not out
any money, so a little incentive, but if you don't agree to
that, מפקעינא ליה מינך, mafkeina lei minach, I will just free him
against your will, tough luck, you're going to be out your money.
Okay, so this is the reverse, not selling him to חוץ לארץ
Chutz La'aretz you get fined, but coming from חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz
to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and we will basically try to pay
you back, but if not, tough luck, he's going free because now
he's in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So that's clearly a different type
of- I mean, it's obviously the flip side of the coin. Okay,
now what's the basis of that? מדרבי אחי ברבי יאשיה, mi-de-Rabbi Achi
be-Rabbi Yoshiya, from the teaching of Rabbi Achi the son of Rabbi
Yoshiya. דתניא דתניא בברייתא. di-tanya di-tanya be-braita. לא ישבו בארצך פן יחטיאו
אותך לי, lo yeshvu be-artzecha pen yachti'u otcha li, they shall not
dwell in your land lest they make you sin against me. יכול
בעובדי כוכבים שקיבל עליו שלא לעבוד עבודת כוכבים הכתוב מדבר, yachol be-ovdei
kochavim she-kibel alav she-lo la-avod avodat kochavim ha-katuv medaber, maybe that would
be true even if they agreed not to be- not, you know,
not to be- worship idols, maybe would they even if they agreed
to convert or let's say at least keep the שבע מצוות בני
נח? Sheva Mitzvot Bnei Noach? I don't know. Let's say keep the
שבע מצוות בני נח, Sheva Mitzvot Bnei Noach, would we not be
allowed to keep them in the land? תלמוד לומר לא תסגיר עבד
אל אדוניו אשר ינצל אליך מעם אדוניו.
talmud lomar lo tasgir eved el adonav asher yinatzel
eleicha me-im adonav. Do not hand back a slave that runs to
you from his master. So somehow we are reading that not as
about slaves, interestingly, but about a- you know- non-Jew who's living in
the land of Israel, we're going to read it back as slaves.
It's a very forced reading. A non-Jew who's living in the land
of Israel who wants to be saved and is running away from
their foreign worship, from their עבודה זרה. avoda zara. And he's coming
to join a monotheistic community, okay, where even if he's not converted.
Okay, so don't- does it somehow apply to the slave? Well no,
no, wait, wait, wait. This is one דרשה. drasha. מאי תקנתו, mai
takanato, so what do you do with him? עמך ישב בקרבך, imcha
yeshev be-kirbecha, let him dwell among you. So if somebody wants to
dwell among us and leave his pagan community, even the שבעת עממין
Shivat Amamim we're allowed to do it. So reading that way has
nothing to do with slaves, it has to do with שבעת עממין,
Shivat Amamim, but very forced read of the פסוק. pasuk. רבי יאשיה
Rebbe Yoshiah did not like this read of the פסוק. Pasuk. האי
מעם אדוניו, Hai me-im Adonav, who's running away to you from his
master? מעם אביו מיבעי ליה, Me-im Aviv mibaya lei, or if you
look at the side, מעם אלוהיו מיבעי ליה. Me-im Elohav mibaya lei.
You're not reading that about a slave and a master, you're reading
about somebody either leaving his community or leaving his God and coming
to you, okay? If you want to read it about שבעה עממים,
Shiva Amamim, okay,
so that's clearly not פשט Pshat in the פסוק. Pasuk. אלא אמר
רבי יאשיה, Ella amar Rebbe Yoshiah, here's פשט Pshat in the פסוק.
Pasuk. במוכר עבדו לחוץ לארץ הכתוב מדבר. Bemocher avdo l'chutz l'aretz hakasuv
medaber. It's actually not why
do we use these tokens, that's actually long literally talking about a
runaway slave, I don't know, but we're talking about something, we're talking
about our משנה Mishnah is in the, is in the פסוק. Pasuk.
Somebody's trying to sell his slave to חוץ לארץ, Chutz l'aretz, and
that's the פשט Pshat of the משנה, Mishnah, okay? אשר ינצל אליך
מעם אדוניו, Asher yinatzel eilecha me-im adonav, don't hand him over, לא
תסגיר, Lo tasgir, אל אדוניו El adonav to the new master, don't
hand him over to the new master, אשר ינצל אליך, Asher yinatzel
eilecha, he is trying to seek refuge and stay in ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, don't hand him over to the new master who's in
חוץ לארץ, Chutz l'aretz, that's how we're reading it, okay? So let's
take a look, because notice it didn't say he ran away, he
said just that לא תסגיר, Lo tasgir, don't hand him over. So
don't hand him over to the new master who bought him in
חוץ לארץ. Chutz l'aretz. If we actually have the case of the
פסוק Pasuk where he ran away from someone in ארץ ישראל... Eretz
Yisrael... Right, we're going to get there, Michael, it's going to be
a third reading. Okay, במוכר עבדו לחוץ לארץ הכתוב מדבר. Bemocher avdo
l'chutz l'aretz hakasuv medaber. So that's the way he reads it, okay.
And therefore you don't, and that's the basis of our משנה. Mishnah.
וקשיא ליה לרבי אחי בריה דרבי יאשיה, Vekashei leh l'Rebbe Achi b'rei
d'Rebbe Yoshiah, so his son, רבי אחי בריה דרבי יאשיה Rebbe Achi
b'rei d'Rebbe Yoshiah didn't like that read, he had a problem. האי
אשר ינצל אליך, Hai asher yinatzel eilecha, that is seeking refuge to
you, אשר ינצל מעמך מיבעי ליה, Asher yinatzel me-imcha mibaya lei, it
should have been that is like, רש"י Rashi explains the difference here,
that, oh, because it's not seeking, rather than reading it that he's
seeking refuge with you, he understood it meant that don't hand him
over that he is trying to be taken from you. So if
it really meant that he was being sold to חוץ לארץ, Chutz
l'aretz, it would have said don't hand him over now that he
is being attempted to be taken away from you. The sense that
he stays by you is only the next פסוק, Pasuk, עמך ישב
בקרבך, Imcha yeshev bekirbecha, שאשר ינצל. She'asher yinatzel. So anyway, so he
says it's not פשט Pshat that he's being sold to חוץ לארץ.
Chutz l'aretz. אלא אמר רבי אחי בריה דרבי יאשיה, Ella amar Rebbe
Achi b'rei d'Rebbe Yoshiah, so here's what רבי אחי Rebbe Achi says
the פסוק Pasuk is talking about, the case we started with, the
עבד Eved finally, a runaway slave, פשט Pshat of the פסוק, Pasuk,
בעבד שברח מחוץ לארץ לארץ הכתוב מדבר. B'eved shebarach m'chutz l'aretz l'aretz
hakasuv medaber. So he ran from חוץ לארץ Chutz l'aretz to ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So don't hand him back to his master, he
is trying to, he's running away from his master, right, אשר ינצל
אליך מעם אדוניו, Asher yinatzel eilecha me-im adonav, he's like trying to
save himself from you away coming away save himself from his master,
don't hand him back, okay, and he stays in the land of
ישראל. Israel. Okay, now of course, so that's a certain פשט Pshat
of the פסוק Pasuk is that it's about a runaway slave and
don't hand him back. The only thing that it added here, which
was missing in the פסוק, Pasuk, is the, right now it does
say עמך ישב בקרבך באחד שעריך בטוב לו, Imcha yeshev bekirbecha b'echad
she'arecha b'tov lo, so it does somehow mention the idea of like
the benefit being in the land, being in your cities, okay, so
it's, but it's still I don't know if the פשט Pshat of
the פסוק Pasuk is that he came from חוץ לארץ. Chutz l'aretz.
Okay, but it's reading it, the emphasis is look you're coming into
the land and he'll stay with you in the land and so
on, so they're reading it as a runaway slave which is פשט
Pshat but particularly with the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael חוץ לארץ Chutz
l'aretz type of an emphasis. But if he ran away in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael then we would give him back. According to that
it would not, yeah you would give him back, exactly, exactly. I
mean even if there's been some sort of unsavory thing, he'd be
mistreated, he runs away, I know, I know, I know, but it's
totally true, we are reading this פסוק Pasuk if a slave runs
away from one place in חוץ לארץ Chutz l'aretz to another place
in חוץ לארץ, Chutz l'aretz, or one place in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael to another place in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you hand him
back. It's only because he's coming from חוץ לארץ, Chutz l'aretz, okay.
תניא אידך, Tanya idach, we taught another ברייתא, Braita, לא תסגיר עבד
אל אדוניו. Lo tasgir eved el adonav. רבי Rebbe אומר omer בלוקח
עבד על מנת לשחררו הכתוב מדבר. B'lokeach eved al m'nas l'shachreru hakasuv
medaber. So basically somebody bought a slave with the agreement to free
him and so now בית דין Beit Din say look, when if
you bought him with the agreement to free him, we're not going
to hand him over to you, right? Do what you promised. So
then you decide you wanted to keep him as a slave, something
like that. היכי דמי, Heichi dami, let's look at the case. אמר
רב דימי בר יצחק, Amar Rav Dimi bar Yitzchak, דכתיב ליה הכי,
Dechasiv lei hachi, he writes as follows, לכשתקנה הרי עצמך קנוי לך
מעכשיו. L'cheshitkaneh harei atzmecha k'nuyeh lach me-achshav. He already wrote him, he
didn't just promise, he wrote him a שטר שחרור, Shtar shichrur, he
said when I purchase you, I here this is your writ of
freedom. Okay, and therefore don't allow this guy now to enslave him.
רב חסדא Rav Chisda ערק ליה עבדא לבי כותאי, Arak lei avda
l'vei Kusai, רב חסדא's Rav Chisda slave ran to the Samaritans. שלח
להו, Shlach lehu, הדרוני ניהלי, Haderoni nihalei, he sent to them give
him back to me. שלח ליה, Shlach lei, לא תסגיר עבד אל
אדוניו, Lo tasgir eved el adonav, they read the פסוק Pasuk like
the פשט, Pshat, right? Well we don't give slaves back, he ran
away, you don't give a slave, a runaway slave back. Now רש"י
Rashi says that the כותים Kutim were in חוץ לארץ, Chutz l'aretz,
but even if they were in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, whatever, they
certainly didn't read it as it's only when it comes from חוץ
לארץ Chutz l'aretz to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. They just read it,
this buddy, we don't give slaves back, end of story, okay, that's
the פסוק, Pasuk, you don't give back a runaway slave. But רב
חסדא Rav Chisda at this time was also out of the land
of Israel, רש"י Rashi says, רב חסדא... Rav Chisda... But anyway, but
they said what difference does it make? Right? It’s all about you
don’t give back a runaway slave. שלחו לו *Shalchu lu* he sent
to them, וכן תעשה לחמורו וכן תעשה לשמלתו וכן תעשה לכל אבדת
אחיך *V'chen ta'aseh lachamoro v'chen ta'aseh l'simlato v'chen ta'aseh l'chol avedat achicha*.
He’s my property! Give it back! What do you mean you’re quoting
me a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* don’t give back a runaway slave, I’ll
quote you a פסוק *pasuk* like give back lost property. שלחו ליה
*Shalchu leh* they sent back to him, I don’t know why these
parentheses, take it out, it makes it so much more richer with
this. שלחו ליה *Shalchu leh* they sent back to him, וכתיב לא
תסגיר עבד אל אדוניו *v'chtiv lo tasgir eved el adonav*. What do
you mean? You’re quoting a פסוק *pasuk* property, we have an explicit
פסוק *pasuk* that says you don’t give back a runaway slave. שלחו
לו *Shalchu lu* he sent to them, ההוא בעבד שברח מחוצה לארץ
לארץ *Hahu b'eved shebarach michutz l'aretz l'aretz*. Don't you know how to
read the פסוק *pasuk*? That's not about a סתם *stam* runaway slave,
that's only when he comes from חוצה לארץ *chutz l'aretz* to ארץ
ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* וכדרבי אחי ברבי יאשיה *u'ch'de'Rabbi Achi b'Rebbi Yoshiya*. Okay.
So that’s why. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ומאי שנא
דשלחו ליה כדרבי אחי ברבי יאשיה *u'mai shna d'shalchu leh k'de'Rabbi Achi
b'Rebbi Yoshiya*? Now I don’t understand the question, like why did they
send him like רבי אחי ברבי יאשיה *Rabbi Achi b'Rebbi Yoshiya*? What
do you mean why he sent him? Because they weren’t buying the
פשט *pshat* of the פסוק *pasuk* without that. דמשמע להו קרא *D'mashma
lehu kra*. Right. No, so that’s the answer, דמשמע להו קרא *d'mashma
lehu kra* because they didn’t understand the פשט *pshat*. Yeah no, but
what’s the alternative? רש״י *Rashi* says he should have sent him like
רבי *Rebbi*. What did רבי *Rebbi* say? Where was רבי *Rebbi*? רבי
*Rebbi* was in the beginning here that the slave ran away and...
where was רבי *Rebbi*? What was רבי *Rebbi*? רש״י *Rashi* says why
wouldn’t they send him like רבי *Rebbi*? Hold on. It had to
do with the כותים *Kutim* I think, doesn’t it? Like who they
were. Yeah obviously. דהכי משמע להו טפי והיכא דלא שמעין דברי חכמים
*D'hachi mashma lehu tfei v'heicha d'lo sham'in divrei chachamim*. Well, ורבי אומר
ובלוקח עבד על מנת לשחררו *V'Rebbi omer u'v'lo'ke'ach eved al m'nat l'shachrero*.
Right. So what do you mean why did he not send... I
don’t understand the question, why not send to them like רבי *Rebbi*?
He didn’t send to them like רבי *Rebbi* because רבי *Rebbi* wouldn’t
have sent... Oh, meaning all he had to say was that that
פסוק *pasuk* doesn't refer to a סתם *stam* case. I see, I
got it, got it. Okay, okay. All he had to say was
that that פסוק *pasuk* does not mean a סתם *stam* case of
a runaway slave. So if so, why did he give them the
רבי יאשיה'ס *Rebbi Yoshiya's* דרשה *drasha*? Give another דרשה *drasha*. And the
answer is because רבי יאשיה'ס *Rebbi Yoshiya's* דרשה *drasha* is the closest
to the פשט *pshat* of the פסוק *pasuk*. So that at least
maybe they could buy. They wouldn't be convinced by the authority of
the חכמים *chachamim* but on the ground... Now even רבי אחי ברבי
יאשיה *Rebbi Achi b'Rebbi Yoshiya* is not the simple פשט *pshat*. The
simple פשט *pshat* is any runaway slave, but at least this דרשה
*drasha* is closer to the פשט *pshat* of the פסוק *pasuk*. Okay.
אביי *Abaye*, bottom line is, the way חז״ל *Chazal* read the פסוקים
*psukim*, you don’t have to give back a runaway slave except in
the special case of חוץ לארץ ארץ ישראל *chutz l'aretz Eretz Yisrael*.
אביי אירכס ליה חמרא בכותאי *Abaye irchas leh chamra b'Kutai*. אביי *Abaye*
lost a donkey who went to the the... the Samaritans. Not a
donkey, a mule. שלחו לו *Shalchu lu* he sent to them, שדרו
ליה *shadru leh* send him back to me. שלחו ליה *Shalchu leh*
they sent to him, צרוך סימנא *tzaruch simana* give us a סימן
*siman*. שלחו לו *Shalchu lu* he sent to them, דחיורא כריסיה *d'chivara
kerisei*. He’s got a white belly. שלחו ליה *Shalchu leh* they sent
back to him, לאו דנחמני את *lav d'Nachmani at* if you weren't
נחמני *Nachmani*, which was his name, if you weren't such a renowned
person, לא הוה משדרינן ליה ניהלך *lo hava meshadrinan leh nehalach* we
would not give him back to you. אטו כולי חמרא לאו כריסייהו
חיורנין נינהו *Atu kulei chamra lav keriseihu chivranin ninhu*? What? All other
mules don't have white bellies? Of course he's got a white belly,
what a silly סימן *siman*, but okay fine, we'll give him back
to you. All right. Like my story about the guy with the
umbrella, right, okay, that's the next... All right. Next משנה *mishna*. אין
פודין *Ein podin*... now, ah, so we’re out of slaves, okay? A
really very rich גמרא *Gemara* about slaves and it ended finally with
a פסוק *pasuk* about runaway slaves. Now back to other תיקון העולם
*tikkun ha'olam* and some of this... And why was this here about
the mule? Because it’s with the כותים *Kutim* and having interactions with
the כותים *Kutim*. Having interaction with כותים *Kutim*. Right, and also, and
also he said give me back my slave, my slave is my
lost donkey that went to you, my lost mule, right, that was
the פסוק *pasuk* that was quoted before. Okay. אין פודין *Ein podin*...
now we get to some really fascinating תיקון העולם *tikkun ha'olam* especially
if you think about contemporary events. אין פודין את השבויים יתר כדי
דמיהן *Ein podin et hashvuyim yoter k'dei d'meihen*. You do not redeem
captives more than their value. Now their value is... who determines the
value? Because it wasn't blackmail, I mean it could have been, but
the idea is in a slave market, now we’ve been primed with
the idea that we’re dealing with slaves, right? So if somebody's taken
captive, what’s their value? How much they go for on the slave
market. But they know that this person is worth a lot more
to you, this is you know, somebody's wife or husband or child.
So don't pay more than their market value. Why not? מפני תיקון
העולם *mipnei tikkun ha'olam*. Because that’s necessary for the betterment of the
world. Not necessary for me, but let’s see what that is in
the גמרא *Gemara*. Okay exactly. ואין מבריחין את השבויים Ve'ein mavrichin et
hashvuyim. *V'ein mavrichin et hashvuyim* and you don't try to basically to
free... an operation? Yeah exactly, to free captives מפני תיקון העולם *mipnei
tikkun ha'olam*. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר מפני תיקון השבויים Tikkun Hashvuyim.
*Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer mipnei tikkun hashvuyim*, for the betterment of
the captives themselves. So this is a really challenging גמרא *Gemara* about
תיקון העולם *tikkun ha'olam*. Let’s see what the גמרא *Gemara* says. Where
else is this גמרא *Gemara*? It’s quoted in כתובות *Ketubot*. איבעיא להו
*Iba'ya lehu*. איבעיא להו *ibaia lehu*, האי מפני תיקון עולם mipnei tikkun
olam. *hai mipnei tikkun haolam* משום דוחקא דציבורא *mishum duchka detzibbura*, why
is it that you don't redeem captives for so much money? Is
it because of that it's just too onerous of a demand on
the ציבור *tzibbur* in terms of the financial cost? או דילמא *o
dilma* משום דלא לגרבו ולייתו טפי *mishum dlo ligrebu velayeisu tefai* because
you don't want to encourage it. Once you're start willing to pay
ransom and pay, and once you're going to negotiate with terrorists, right,
then you're just going to encourage future type of behavior. So you
have to deal with this terrible tragedy right now, but it's in
the big picture, that's what's necessary. So which one is it? And
there's a big נפקא מינה nafka mina *nafka mina*. The גמרא *Gemara*
says תא שמע *ta shema* דלוי בר דרגא *deLevi bar Darga* פרקיה
לברתיה *parkei lbarteih*, he redeemed his daughter בתליסר אלפי דינרי זהב *btlisar
alfei dinarei zahav* with 13,000 gold dinars. So clearly it was יתר
על כדי דמיהן *yeter al kdei dmeihen*. How do we allow it?
Well, if it's only because of the financial cost to the ציבור
*tzibbur*, we'd allow an individual to do whatever he or she wants.
But if it's because of the policy, we cannot do this to
encourage future behavior, we should not allow even individuals to act this
way. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, אמר amar, אביי *amar Abaye*, אביי
*Abaye* said, ומאן לימא לן דברצון חכמים עבד *uman leima lan debiratzon
chachamim avad*? Who tells you that that was done with the approval
of the sages? דלמא שלא ברצון חכמים עבד *dilma shelo biratzon chachamim
avad*, maybe not approval? So we don't know. And this became a
big issue for the Jews in the Middle Ages. I think people
know that it's an issue now to negotiate with terrorists, where we
say we don't negotiate with terrorists, and then of course we do
negotiate with terrorists. We allow a family to do it, we allow
a family to do it, but we won't as a government. Right,
it's also, that's an interesting point. Right, right, right, so the policy
is as a government as opposed to, right, but okay, that's a
good point. And also people might know the famous מהר"ם מרוטנבורג *Maharam
miRothenburg* was held in prison and he refused to let people redeem
him because they were charging an obscene amount and he—אין פודין את
השבויים *ein podin es hashevuyim*—he refused to let the Jewish community redeem
him. And then the sad irony is that he died in prison
and then once he was dead, they basically paid an obscene amount
to get back his body and to bury his body. So definitely
been dealing with these cases. Obviously it comes up nowadays in terms
of terrorists. And look at תוספות *Tosafot* about this issue. דלא לגרבו
ולייתו *delo ligrebu velayeisu*, תוספות *Tosafot* says, והא דתניא בפרק נערה *vha
dtanya bperek Naarah* נשבית והיו מבקשין ממנה עשרה בדמיה *nishbeis vhayu mevakshin
mimena asara bdameha*, a woman was taken captive and they were asking
ten times her value—פעם ראשון פודה *paam rishon podeh*, the first time
he actually has, he has to redeem. He, the husband. He, the
husband. שאני אשתו דהויא כגופו יותר מבתו *shani ishto dehavya kgufo yoter
mibito*. Okay, דהכא *dehacha*. דעל עצמו לא תיקנו שלא יתן כל אשר
לו בעד נפשו *deal atzmo lo tiknu shelo yitein kol asher lo
bad nafsho*. It says even in the הוה אמינא *hava amina* that
it was for the betterment of society to not encourage that behavior,
would we say you could not redeem yourself? Right, let's say you
could basically transfer funds, you have your money, whatever, they took you
captive. So certainly we wouldn't say you couldn't save yourself, whatever the
bigger societal issue is, we're not going to do it to the
point that you actually have to give, can't take care of your
own immediate self-interest. So once that's true, we're going to let you
redeem your wife as well. But not your daughter. So you're allowed
to pay as much as you want to get yourself out? To
get yourself out and to get your wife out. Once whatever the
reason is, we're going to obviously make an exception for you, for
yourself and for your wife. I don't know. Anyway, but interestingly, but
not your daughter. Okay. רבי יהושע בן חנניה דפרקיה לההוא תינוק בממון
הרבה בנזיקין *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya deparkei lhahu tinok bmamon harbe bNezikin*.
Another story where a certain young kid was redeemed with a lot
of money and he was by a rabbi—לפי שהיה מופלג בחכמה *lefi
shehaya muflag bchochma*. Okay, what about if somebody is very valuable to
the community? This is a future prodigy. Is that what they're saying?
It was יותר *yoter*. No, I don't know what you mean. I
mean there was יותר על כדי דמיהן *yoter al kdei dmeihen*, but
it was there was a larger need at stake. It was this
is a valuable person in the community, he's going to be a
prodigy, we need to get him back. I guess not. אי נמי
בשעת חורבן הבית לא שייך דלא לגרבו *ei nami bshaas churban habayis
lo shayach dlo ligrebu*. Okay, that was anyway in a time when
anyway they were going to do what they were going to do,
they didn't need our encouragement. Okay, so here's really interesting questions. How
do you balance this idea of it's going to have a negative
impact on the larger community, but how does that constrain my ability
to take care of my own interests, right? And when do we
allow for certain things or counterbalancing concerns of like this person also,
we need this person back, he's our nuclear scientist, if we don't
get him back, that also has a big impact on the community.
Right? So how do you balance those types of issues? The other
really interesting thing about this גמרא *Gemara* is there was a really
good article, I don't think some of my liberal friends liked this
article, but it was by what's his name? I can't remember his
name. I think it was by Leon Wieseltier, I might be wrong.
Anyway, it was called "How to Not Redeem the World". And it
was a critique of a book about תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam, *tikkun
olam* by all of these different Jewish writers that wrote on every
topic under the sun about תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam *tikkun olam*. And
basically said any single topic you want to write on, you are
able to, you find some תורה *Torah* source and some Jewish source
to say, look, this is the right liberal, it believes in this
liberal cause and it's תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam *tikkun olam* or whatever,
and you're able to cherry-pick some sources. And says and this doesn't
really seriously engage the serious way the תורה *Torah* sources grapple with
these serious issues and really embrace the tensions that are present in
the sources. And he brings— this סוגיא, which is about תיקון עולם,
Tikkun Olam and he says, you know, sometimes the most immediate feel-good
response is not necessarily, right, the best thing for the, you know,
for the sort of big picture type of issue and that liberals
have a way, and I'm saying this as a liberal, and believe
me, and he says liberals have a way of casting conservatives as
uncaring, whereas maybe there's some people that actually do very much care
but don't think that the quick fix immediate response is the best
way of solving deep systemic problems. And here דווקא davka the תיקון
עולם Tikkun Olam is to not do anything. Right? The תיקון עולם
Tikkun Olam, in this case is to not save that person who
was taken captive because that's seen as what's necessary to be done
ultimately to deal at a deeper level with the issues. So, I'm
not saying that I necessarily agree with all of the politics of
all of the situations, but it raises really important points. Number one,
I agree with that, the problem when people basically have already decided
what their issue is and then just find the source to support
it, you know, and sort of cherry-pick the sources is a problem
rather than really engaging. And one of the beauties of הלכה Halakha
is that הלכה Halakha really does not just these abstract values, brings
them into the real world and grapples with the trade-offs that come
about when you have to make real decisions. And there are real
costs to certain types of decisions. So it really is fascinating that
the תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam here is to not just, oh my
god, somebody's in trouble, we gotta save that person. Like actually the
תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam might be to don't do anything. That's the
תיקון עולם, Tikkun Olam you know? So it's a challenging idea, yes.
I feel like it's a... this is an exception, though, in the
way that we see human life, no? Like this is... I mean
generally... Right, of course, generally we do everything. So that's the point,
but a serious engagement in תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam makes us think
about one minute, don't just immediately go by where your sort of
moral, you know, sort of, you know, intuition is driving you, like
think about the cost, think about the bigger issues that are at
play. My sense is like the way we deal with human life
normally we think don't think about that, you know, like one life
is like, it doesn't matter, break שבת, Shabbat, break whatever. We don't
like do like the חשבונות Cheshbonot of like, oh we'll save this
person and we'll sacrifice this person, like we're learning the גמרא as
we're learning, ideological, one life is worth everything and this is like
an exception. Right, but sometimes there is, because sometimes there's like, well
if you save this life then you lose ten lives, and you
know, sometimes you have to make those חשבונות Cheshbonot and that's part
of I think that's part of the point. Like sometimes you have
to be thinking תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam is about thinking about big
picture. But so he's not denying that the basic, obviously, like some
of these basic issues... like that's the point that the values of,
you know, sort of the general liberal values about caring for the
disenfranchised and the marginalized and valuing life and all those types of
things, but then there's the... sometimes the תיקון עולם Tikun Olam is
about thinking about how that's going to play out. It's a challenging
point and I think it's a very legitimate one. Very briefly, I
mean, I don't... it's assumed that... it doesn't say specifically that they're
going to kill him if you don't, right? Right, but I... that
is true, it doesn't say that, and I think you're right that
the while in Jewish literature, פדיון שבויים Pidyon Shvuyim is treated automatically
as פיקוח נפש, Pikuach Nefesh, right? and that gets to Jenna's point
that it's human life. But I think probably in most cases it
was more about no, just a life of enslavement, you know עבירות,
Aveirot, probably חילול שבת Chillul Shabbat and eating טרפות treifus and enslavement,
but nevertheless it most cases and maybe... depending on the case it
could have also been about sexual abuse, right? but it was not...
it was usually not about like they weren't going to kill you,
you know, you were a valuable asset, you know? Does the calculus
change if you know they're going to kill you? In other words,
then you can't sacrifice? Yeah, I don't know. That raises some of
the questions that Jenna raised. Sometimes אין דוחין נפש מפני נפש, Ein
Dochin Nefesh Mipnei Nefesh, but sometimes we make other types of חשבונות,
Cheshbonot, you know, and some of it, so you know, that does
become... it does raise different types of a calculus. And I think
there was even an additional or different rationale with the ransom, with
the payment for the soldiers that were captured in Israel, had to
do with the morale of the army. Right? In other words, if
you can rely on the they will save us, then our morale
as military will not be... will not be demoralized. Right, right, right.
But a lot of people, you know, very obviously, you know, compassionate
people were deeply against that because, you know, you're freeing all these
future potential future murderers. Right, right. Alright, so those are the hard
questions, you know. Okay, that's exactly what we're dealing with. Let's take
a look. ואין פודים את השבויים מפני תיקון עולם. Ve'ein podin et
hashvuyim mipnei tikkun olam. I'm sorry. ואין מבריחין את השבויים. You don't
basically try to save these captives... מפני תיקון עולם. Tikun Olam, I'm
sorry. מפני תיקון שבויים. mipnei tikkun shvuyim. מאי בינייהו? mai beinayhu? What's
the difference? What, you know, what is תיקון עולם here anyway? So
איכא בינייהו דליכא אלא חד. ika beinayhu d'leika ela chad. There's only
one meaning. Is it that if you try to save them and
you fail, then they are going to now... you know, is the
concern about what they're going to do to the remaining captives? Forget
you fail, you succeed. Okay, but what are they going to do
to the remaining captives? Right? That's תיקון השבויים. What the תיקון עולם
is that if you're able to successfully free this group of captives
in the future future, they're going to be much more, they're going
to have, they're not going to have רחמנות, rachmanus, they're going to
have them in chains and be much more oppressive and do all
these types of things to prevent them, you know, they'll go easy
on them if they know that they're, you know, not easy, but
whatever, anyway, they'll be, they won't be as, you know, as oppressive
if they, if they're not if they're not afraid that they're going
to be seized back. Okay, so the נפקא מינה would be if
it's about future then no matter how definite you are that you're
going to succeed right here and nobody is going to suffer in
the immediate here and now, you're afraid about what the consequences will
be in the future. That's תיקון עולם is being concerned about the
larger picture, the big picture. תיקון שבויים Tikun Shvuyim is right now
you're going to do this and you're going to save a few
of them, what are the, what are the reprisals that they're going
to do to everybody who's left behind, right? So that's the immediate
issue. And so if nobody's left behind, I don't have to worry
about reprisals. Okay. Okay, בנתיה דרב נחמן, Bantei de-Rav Nachman, so now
we'll end I guess with a very interesting story. בנתיה דרב נחמן,
Bantei de-Rav Nachman, Rav Nachman's daughters, בחו קדרה בידייהו, bachshu kederah be-yadayehu,
they were able to stir a boiling pot with their directly with
their hands. So well, what was going on there? That was like
a נס. nes. So קשיא ליה לרב עיליש, kashya leh le-Rav Illish,
Rav Illish didn't understand how could they be so righteous to be
saved by this miracle? הכתיב, ha-ketiv, the פסוק says אדם אחד מאלף
מצאתי, adam echad me-elef matzati, only one out of a thousand men
was I able to find that was righteous ואישה בכל אלה לא
מצאתי ve-ishah be-chol eleh lo matzati and I couldn't and a woman
certainly, you know, even one in a thousand men, a woman of
course not. So how he, how could that be? בנתיה דרב נחמן,
Bantei de-Rav Nachman, what about Rav Nachman's daughters? So it seems like
there are righteous women out there. Okay, רמא להו מילתא, rama lehu
milta, so something one things came about ואשתביין ve-ishtavyan and the daughters
were taken captive ואשתבאי איהו נמי בהדייהו ve-ishtavai ihu nami bahadayehu and
he was taken captive with them. יומא חד הוה יתיב גבי ההוא
גברא דהוה ידע בלשנא דציפורי. yoma chad hava yativ gabei hahu gavra
de-hava yada be-lishna de-tziporei. One day he was sitting by a person
who could understand the language of birds. אתא עורבא, ata urva, raven
came וקרא ליה ve-kara leh and called out to him, the guy
who could, the bird whisperer or whatever. אמר ליה, amar leh, he
says to him מאי קאמר, mai ka-amar, what was that raven saying?
אמר ליה, amar leh, he said to him עיליש ברח עיליש ברח,
Illish berach Illish berach, it was saying Illish run away, Illish run
away, like you can now escape the captive. אמר, amar, עורבא שקרא
הוא, urva shikra hu, ah ravens are liars ולא סמיכנא עליה, ve-lo
samichna aleh, I don't trust him. אדהכי אתא יונה, ade-hachi ata yonah,
he didn't, he wasn't afraid that the guy who understood the language
of birds was lying, he was only afraid that the birds were
the liars. Anyway, then a certain dove came וקרא ve-kara and was
calling out. אמר ליה, amar leh, מאי קאמר, mai ka-amar, what's the
dove saying? אמר ליה, amar leh, he said to him עיליש ברח
עיליש ברח, Illish berach Illish berach, same thing. אמר, amar, כנסת ישראל
כיונה מתילא, Knesset Yisrael ke-yonah metila, ah the nation of Israel is
compared to a יונה, yonah, to a bird, to a dove, like
in שיר השירים, Shir HaShirim, שמע מינה מתרחיש לי ניסא, shma mina
mitrachish li nisa, see that a miracle will come to me if
I try to run away. By the way, this points out Tosafot's
point, we don't try to free captives because of תיקון עולם, it
doesn't mean that the captives are not allowed to run away themselves,
sort of like Tosafot about you're allowed to redeem yourself. Whatever we're
doing for the betterment of the world, you can take care, you
can protect your own your own self first. Okay, so that's how
this is fitting in, I mean that does piece, but besides this
whole thing with the daughters, that's sort of the important story also
that you can save yourself. Okay, אמר, amar, איזיל, izil, he said
I'll go אחזי בנתיה דרב נחמן, achzei Bantei de-Rav Nachman, אי קיימן
בהימנותייהו, i kaiman be-heimanutaihu, now let me before I run away, let
me go ahead and check out Rav Nachman's daughters who are also
being held by these captors. If they kept the faith, they have
not given themselves over sexually to their captors, אדרינהו, adrinhu, I'll take
them back with me. אמר, amar, so אמר, and then he said,
נשי כל מילי דאית להו, nashi kol milei de-it lehu, women whenever
they have some secret to share סדרן להדדי בבית הכיסא, sadran le-hadadei
be-veit ha-kisei, they, you know, get together in the bathroom and that's
when they share their secrets. שמעינהו, shamainhu, so he went over, so
he went, he went to eavesdrop by the bathroom. שמעינהו דקאמרן, shamainhu
de-ka-amran, he heard them saying עדי גוברין ונהרדאי גוברין, adei guvrin u-neharda-ei
guvrin, we used to have husbands and now our these Nehardaim these
these are our husbands. לימרו להו לשבוייהו, leimru lehu le-shavuyaihu, so you
know we had those were our husbands before, these are our husbands
now. So what's the difference? לימרו להו לשבוייהו, leimru lehu le-shavuyaihu, let's
go tell our captors דלרחקינו מהכא, de-lerachkinu me-hacha, to we should move,
we should get further away from where we were, you know, where
we had been living until now until now before we were taken
captive. דלא ליתו אינשי ולישמעו וליפרקונו, de-la leitu inshi ve-lishme-u ve-lifre-kunu, so
our husbands shouldn't find out and they shouldn't redeem us. I like
these Nehardaim, they're much nicer husbands than our old husbands, let's just
try to move away. So clearly they had given themselves over sexually,
they had not kept the faith, they were happy. So clearly they're
not righteous women. So clearly they're not righteous women, well that's the
whole story, right. Point out what their marriages must have been like
first. Very, thank you, that that is a very good point. They
were also saving themselves. Well, right, and they might feel, right, and
then they... By giving themselves over sexually and not resisting, they're given
a life and they're not being treated as slaves and they're not
being raped and whatever, exactly. Exactly. But I think part of the
message is that they seem to be totally—it wasn't just a way
of compromising. They seemed happy with the situation. They wanted, they proactively
were saying, let's move away from here anyway. So that's the story.
So they really weren't anyway צדיקים. Tzadikim. So קם ארק, Kam Arak,
so he got up, ran away, and he didn't take them with
him obviously. אזל איהו Azal ihu ודהוא גברא. ve-dahu gavra. Now, and
that bird-listener came, went with him. He figured, hey, if he's going
to escape, I might as well go with him, he's going to
be safe. לדידי אתרחיש ניסא. Ledidi itrachish nisa. For him, a miracle
happened. עבר במברא. Avar bemavra. He was able to cross over a
stream of water and escape from the captors. ודהוא גברא, Vedahu gavra,
that person, אשכחוהו, ashkachuhu, they found him, וקטלוהו, vekatluhu, and they killed
him. Okay? So obviously, this was only a special opportunity given to
Rav Ilish. Anybody else would have been killed. Right. So maybe if
the women would have gone with him, they would have been killed
too. כי הדר ואתא אמר. Ki hadar ve-ata amar. So when he
finally came back, he said, now I understand, they weren't so righteous.
הוו קבשי כדורי בכשפים. Havei kavshi kadeira be-chashafim. It must be the
opposite, that they were actually witches and that they were able to
stir the pot with their witchcraft and that's how they succeeded. So
that's a really lovely story to end with. It certainly is. We
will end with that.